我们的星球上遍布着50亿公里的道路
Five billion kilometres of roads
network our planet.
我可不喜欢这边的悬崖，
300-400英尺的悬崖
I don't like the drop down
this side, 300-400 feet drop.
那会立刻毙命。
Instant death then.
然而交流和贸易的渴望意味着
Yet the desire to communicate
and trade means new routes
新路线正日渐开辟在险恶的地形上
are being forged through
increasingly challenging terrain.
尽可能的接近那个地方。
我知道，但是我能搞定那个悬崖吗？
Keep as close as you can there.
I know, but am I OK with that drop?
横渡北极苔原。
Across Arctic tundra.
可见度为零的路途。
我们正在迷茫中行进。
Zero visibility on the pass.
We are mid-drift.
翻过山口。
Over mountain passes.
穿过丛林
不，走，佛格！走
Through jungle.
No! Go, Fogle! Go!
这些道路是跟大自然的一场持久战
These roads fight a
constant battle with nature.
让我们使之平息吧。
Let's just calm it down.
而他们真实的存在是人类
巧夺天工的证明。
But their very existence is
testament to man's ingenuity,
驾驭他们需要勇气和决心。
and driving them requires
courage and determination.
啊！
Oh, ge... Woah!
探险家本佛格和喜剧演员修丹尼
组队征服这条横穿秘鲁的险路
Adventurer Ben Fogle and comedian
Hugh Dennis have teamed up to drive
the treacherous route across Peru,
从安第斯深入亚马逊腹地
from the Andes
into the very heart of the Amazon.
在这传奇的8天之旅，
他们将领略到这条非凡之路的峻美
On this epic eight-day journey,
they will see the beauty and the
danger of this extraordinary road.
他们的目标是到达秘鲁的中心
They are aiming to get to the
geographical centre of Peru.
现在尽可能靠近那一边。
As close to that side
as you can, now.
他们所选择的道路有着两人都
And the road they're taken has
some of the most extreme
前所未遇的极端行车条件
driving conditions either of them
have ever encountered.
小心点。小心点。
Careful, careful.
他们需要稳定的手法才能顺利度过，
还需要坚定的意志。
To make it through, they will need
steady hands and nerves of steel
在世界上最危险的道路之一
on one of the world's
most dangerous roads.
本和修的路途开始于海拨超过3000
米的地方，在秘鲁安第斯山
Ben and Hugh's journey begins
at over 3,000 metres above sea level
in the Peruvian Andes.
那么，你紧张吗？
So, are you nervous
about this at all?
稍微紧张。我能确认一件事吗？
I'm slightly nervous about it.
Can I just check one thing?
你是第一次考过驾照吗？
Did you pass your
driving test first time?
不是第一次。
I didn't pass my
driving test first time.
有什么关系吗？好的。
你考过几次？
That matter? That's fine.
How many times did you take it?
7次，7次？7次？
Seven. Seven times? Seven?
我想这顺便使我成为更好的驾驶员
I like to think it makes me
a better driver, by the way.
那很好。因为我从没通过。
That's fine, because
I've never passed one.
7次！这让我感觉好多了...
Seven times!
That makes me feel so much better...
他们的路线长1000K,横渡秘鲁,
Their route runs for 1,000k across
Peru and will take them through
将使他们穿过各种各异的有挑战
性的不同地带.
three very different but
challenging types of terrain.
他们还得穿过安第斯山,在秘鲁最
高的道路之一之上
They have to cross the Andes
on one of Peru's highest roads,
在驶向亚马孙雨林之前
before heading down into
the Amazon Rainforest.
在那之后,去波苏索的镇上有500公里
的艰苦丛林路
After that,
it's 500 kilometres of rough
jungle roads to the town of Pozuzo.
最终,他们需要穿过卡班巴大峡谷
Finally, they will have to make it
across the mighty Huancabamba Canyon
再沿着几英里的泥巴路达到秘鲁
中心
and along miles of mud roads
to reach the centre of Peru.
他们希望在这儿找到康斯提图松,
1980年代一个打算替代利马的城市
Here they hope to find Constitucion,
a city which in the 1980s was
intended to replace Lima
作为秘鲁的新首都.但是今天
甚至在地图上消失
as Peru's new capital but today
doesn't even appear on the map.
但是他们的冒险始于在康塞城的
秘鲁的安第斯山的大门
But their adventure begins at
the gateway to the Peruvian Andes
in the town of Concepcion.
这是当地人进山的路的起点
This is where local people come
to start their journey into
这儿的出租车司机知道回去的路
the mountains and the taxi drivers
here know this route backwards.
本发现跟他们有使用他那发霉
的西班牙语的机会
Ben sees an opportunity to try
out his rusty Spanish on them.
（西班牙语）（打招呼）
Hola. Mi nombre es Ben.
我们在我们车上
Somos en nuestro coche.
We're in our car.
Que bueno, que bueno.
之间的路怎么样？
Digame, que tal es la carratera? How
is the road between here and there?
他说路很危险有很多...
So he's saying the roads are very
dangerous and there's lots of...
灰尘
Polvo is dust.
灰尘扬起,你什么也看不见.
有大的山崖吗?
It comes up and you can't see
anything. Are there big drops?
哦!500到1000米的悬崖.
Ooh! 500 to 1,000 metre drops.
康塞城?不,康士城
Concepcion? No, Constitucion.
司机们似乎不太了解康城这个城市
The drivers don't seem to know
much about the city of Constitucion,
除了知道它在丛林中的某个地方
except that it's
somewhere in the jungle.
那么我们没事吗?
So will we be OK?
他说最大的危险是其他司机,
He said the biggest danger
is other drivers, and he said
我们必须在转弯非常,非常小心
said we have to be very, very
careful on all the corners.
再加上,我们不得不担心你.
我也不得不担心自己
Plus we have to worry about you.
And I have to worry about me.
谢谢
Gracias, senor. Gracias.
再见
Hasta luego.
好的，我们上路啦
OK, let's hit the road.
了解了当地路况，
他们迅速出发。
Armed with local knowledge,
they're aiming for a quick getaway.
但是这条路暂时关闭
But the road has been
temporarily closed.
我发现令人惊奇的是我们
不知身在何处
I find it amazing
we're in the middle of nowhere
我们偶遇了最大
从没见过的铜管乐队比赛
太神奇了，是不是？
and we've come across the biggest
brass-band competition I've
ever seen. It's amazing, isn't it?
我以为我从不会见到一只铜管乐队
I don't think I've ever
seen a brass-band competition.
你之前从哪儿见过？
Where have you seen one before?
你以前见过吗？
Have you ever seen one?
35之乐队，来自全秘鲁
在道路解封之前，游行走过城镇
35 bands from all over Peru
will parade through town today
before the road re-opens.
你觉得这是件很酷的是吗？
你是小孩吗？
You think this is a cool thing
to do, then? If you're a kid?
你认为管选乐队有小孩吗？
Do you think the cool kids
are in the brass band?
你会觉得这一切很傻吗？
Would you think it's all the dweebs?
我不知道，我觉得很酷
I don't know. I think it's cool.
是吗？是的。
Do you? Yeah.
如果我在那儿，我也会在乐队里
If I was out here,
I'd be in a brass band.
你认为我们现在该不该从这个地方
出去？
Do you think we'll ever actually
get out of this place now?
好的，来了更多的。
Well, there are more coming.
那是我的最爱。
That lot are my favourite.
我认为他们要赢了
I think they're going to win.
我们该回车上了吧？
Shall we head back to the car?
我们能出来吗？我认我我们应该
走这条路
Can we get out, do you think?
I think we should go this way.
出发之后，蜿蜒的道路升入世界第二的山脉
安第斯山
After Conception, the road quickly
rises up into the Andes - the second
highest mountain range in the world.
从山上到亚马逊的路线是由
方济会的修道士们约500年前绘制的
This route over the mountains and
into the Amazon was mapped out by
Franciscan monks
almost 500 years ago
在他们探寻并教化土著部落皈依的时候
as they searched for indigenous
tribes to convert to Christianity.
我们上了4500米了现在，
在阿尔卑斯那几乎是蒙特白的顶部了
We're about 4,500 metres up now,
so in Alps terms that's
almost the top of Mont Blanc.
今天，庞大的无峰驼群和羊驼群
漫游在这片区域。
Today, huge herds of llama
and alpaca roam this area,
躲开他们将成为小伙子们的第一个
挑战。
and avoiding them is going to
be the boys' first challenge.
我们走了。
Here we go.
哦...劳驾.劳驾
Oh... Woah.. Excuse us. Excuse us!
嘿.好家伙.
这个避开了路.
Hey, chaps.
That one's getting out of the way.
这个没有.
你以前见过羊驼吗?
This one isn't.
Have you seen an alpaca before?
是的.他们真酷.
Yeah. They're pretty cool.
我一直想成为一个牧羊人来着
I've always wanted to
be an alpaca farmer.
好的.你会的.你可以在英格了
干,是不是?
Well, you could. You can do
that in England, can't you?
尽管跟在安第斯这儿十分不同,是吗?
It's not quite the same as
here in the Andes though, is it?
几年来我很有幸的来过秘鲁几次
I've been lucky enough
to come to Peru a couple
of times over the years.
我大约18的时候,刚毕业,来过.
所以这是我获得学习经历的地方
I came here when I was about 18
and fresh out of school, so this is
where I had my learning experience.
这是我发现自我的地方,对于我来说,
这是我所热爱和感到非常振奋的地方
It's where I found myself, as such.
So, for me, it's somewhere I really
love and I get very excited by still.
受到他第一次秘鲁之旅的启发,
本在拉美攻读了一个学位.
Inspired by his first trip to Peru,
Ben took a degree in Latin American
作为一个职业探险家,学习,往返
南美很多次
studies and has since returned
to South America many times
as a professional adventurer.
Is that a road?
那是一条路吗?
向上去的那是一条路吗?
Is that thing a road going up there?
一定是.蜿蜒曲折,,,我不知道我们是不是
这么上去.
It must be.
With the switchbacks... I don't know
if that's what we're going up.
看上去是条荒路,是吗?
It looks very off-road, doesn't it?
见鬼!
Bloody hell.
我从没去过拉美
我从没去过南美
I've never been to Latin America.
I've never been to South America.
我去过所有的大洲,除了那儿.
I've been to all the other
continents but I've never been here.
我很高兴做这件事。
I'm so pleased I'm doing it.
这是一个美妙的旅程。
This is a fantastic journey.
这个旅程将使得修的游客历程
比以前更深一步，
It's a journey that will take
Hugh further off the tourist
trail than he's ever been before.
科马斯城建成于超过2000年前
The town of Comas was established
over 2,000 years ago.
但是第一辆机动车在1930年代才出现
在这里，当道路工人
But the first vehicles only appeared
here in the 1930s, when road crews
终于围绕着村子凿通了山路
finally blasted through the
mountains surrounding the village.
这是最后的机会，在进丛林之前，
It's the last chance before
the jungle for drivers to check
由当地的机械师，瑞，来检查一下
轮胎能否胜任过擦。
that their tyres are up to scratch
with local mechanic, Rui Cardenas.
(西语）
Hola.
Mi nombre es Ben. Gusto, gusto.
我想说，我们不太了解轮胎，
这个公平吗？你了解吗？
I'm going to say...
Is it fair for me to say we don't
know much about tyres? Do you?
我是不是自以为是？
Am I being presumptuous there?
没有，说的很坦白。
No, it'd be fair to say.
他说西班牙语
HE SPEAKS SPANISH
我就是说，如果出现了一个小孔，
我们又没有空余的内胎什么的咋办
I'm just saying what happens if
there's a hole and we don't have
spare inner tubes or anything.
哦，你就把轮胎里面垫草
Wow, you're thatching
the inside of a tyre.
所以他说最好用树叶什么的
So he's saying the best thing
is to use leaves and things.
在我看来，这真的是大黄叶柄
最好的用途。
This would be, in my opinion,
the very best use for rhubarb.
他说我们实际上同样可以把衣服
放进去。
So he's saying we can actually
put our clothes in here as well.
你的夹克。
用你的衣服。
Your jacket. Use your clothes!
他说，我们可以借用这个。
He's saying we can borrow his.
我们在这一步还不需要把你填满
We don't need to stuff you
in there at this stage.
他们真实应有尽有，是不是？
我想那是你该做的。
They're so resourceful out here,
aren't they?
I suppose that's what you have to do.
你需要能用的都用上
You have to just make do
with what you have.
(西语）
Y cuantos? Mucha mucha?
直到它相当得牢固。
Until it's pretty solid.
你认为这会通过英国的MOT吗？
Do you think that'd pass
the MOT in England?
这让你好奇为什么还要麻烦的充满气
It makes you wonder why
they bother to fill them with air.
大概他说的是，没有外国人这么疯狂
的来走这条路
Roughly what he was saying there
are that no foreigners are
crazy enough to come on this road.
在他们的教训结束的时候，一天快结束了
At the end of their lesson
the day is nearly over,
这条路的下一步，太危险了，
以至于不能在黑夜行车。
the next stage of the road is too
dangerous to drive in the dark.
所以他们不得不在科马斯过夜
So they have to spend
the night in Comas.
他们的路边旅馆是餐馆的2倍
Their roadside hotel
doubles up as a restaurant
为每天来往这条线路的人提供餐宿
to feed and house the people
who drive this route every day.
今天，菜单上只有一道菜
Today, there is
only one dish on the menu.
我不介意一天吃的饭菜，在英国时，
而且你大概会知道你会遇到的情况
I don't mind eating the dish of the
day when I'm in England and you know
roughly what you're going to get.
(西语）
Buenas noches. Que tal?
(西语）谢谢
Gracias.
看看前头
Have a look at the head area.
那是头，，，
That's a guinea pig.
牙齿，排骨
Teeth, ribs...
那是他的心脏吗？
Is that its heart?
我认为他们叫它QUIQUI
Qui qui I think is what they call it.
如果没人告诉你那是什么，
我觉得你可能认为那是鸡
If nobody told you what
that was, I think you'd
just think that was chicken.
很明显那是什么。
It's fairly obvious what it is.
所缺少的唯一的线索是它不是
装在笼子里。
The only clue it's missing
is that it's not in a hutch.
我们在开吃这种天竺鼠（几内亚猪）的玩笑，
可是这是一种他们在外就餐所吃的
We're joking about eating
guinea pig but this is
kind of what they eat out here.
我总是敏感的避免嘲笑别人的文化
和饮食。
·I always feel sensitive about not
wanting to laugh at other people's
cultures and what they eat.
不，绝对没有什么不好。
他们在卧室里养
No, no that's absolutely fine.
They keep them in their bedrooms.
就是那种睡觉的大卧室，
天竺鼠（几内亚猪）谁在床底下，
也许有60只
Like the long rooms they sleep in,
the guinea pigs, maybe up to 60,
sleep under the bed
并且用处很多，像个加热器似的，
它们整晚的到处活动
and multipurpose, like a heater,
they move around all night
他们制造的热量贯穿床板，
保持暖和
and the heat they make goes up
through the bed, keeps them warm
然后，他们吃它们做早餐，
我很小的时候就吃过天竺鼠（几内亚猪）
and then they eat them for breakfast.
I had guinea pigs when I was
我记得，他们也互相吞噬。
a child, and as I remember,
they ate each other.
本和修已经完成了他们旅程的
第一阶段。
Ben and Hugh have completed
the first stage of their journey,
但是他们一直以来享受到的柏油碎石
路面在科马斯戛然而止。
but the tarmac road they've enjoyed
so far ends abruptly in Comas.
现在他们得行驶150公里的没铺过
的山路来翻越安第斯，
Now they have to drive
150 kilometres over the Andes
然后驶向塞提波的丛林城镇。
on an unpaved mountain road,
and then down to
the jungle town of Satipo.
单行的科马斯之路伸向超过4500米的高度
The single-track
Comas road reaches heights
of over 4,500 metres.
综合了发髻一般的弯道和险峻陡峭
的悬崖，使得这段路成了南美最具
挑战性的险路之一
Its hairpin bends and
sheer drops combine to
make it one of the most challenging
drives anywhere in South America.
看呀
Look.
那一定是我们要找的路。
That must be our road.
那是我们要走的路。
不可思议。
That is our road.
That is unbelievable.
太奇妙了。
你们是怎么建造出那样的路的？
This is fantastic.
How do you build a road like that?
非同凡响
It's just extraordinary.
哇。
就是一条非常险峻的悬崖在那儿。
Wow.
It's quite a steep drop just here.
是的，我看见了
Yep, I saw that.
我在提醒这一点
I was aware of that.
科马斯之路在整个40年代由庞大的劳力
施工队在山腰里雕刻出来。
The Comas road was carved out of the
mountainside by huge gangs of manual
labourers throughout the 1940s.
工程师们遵从的草图是早在百多年前
的传教士们设计的
Its engineers followed the track
charted by the missionaries
centuries earlier.
悬崖到下面的山谷超过1000米。
With drops of over 1,000 metres
to the valley below,
哪怕一点小小的误差都会导致灾难
even the smallest miscalculation
can lead to disaster.
你在那儿看见过山崩吗？
Do you see the landslide there?
不要太企盼这个，因为这儿还会有
Don't be looking at it too much,
because this is also here.
看，从那儿下去就是谷底也是你
生命的结束
Look, down there is
the bottom of the valley
and also the end of your life.
看这条上去的路
Look at the road going up.
要想从科马斯之路生还，你需要
对此稀有景观闭上一只眼。
And to survive on the Comas road,
it also pays to keep an eye
on the rear-view mirror.
OK，我们后边来了辆巴士
OK, we've got a bus behind us.
我不想乘坐巴士
I would not want to be in a bus.
Would you?
好的，乘巴士的情况是，你的命运
掌握在了一个你一无所知的司机手上
Well, the thing is about a bus
is that you're in the hands of some
driver you know nothing about.
哦，那跟我们很相像
Oh, that's like us!
的确如此
Exactly.
他也比你走的快
He's also going faster than you.
喇叭声
HORN SOUNDS
他在冲我鸣笛
He honked at me!
旁边就是1000英尺的悬崖什么的
With 1,000-foot drop,
or whatever that is, next to me.
我们让他们超车吗？
Do we let him pass us?
在继续走一点，是吗？
Keep going for a bit. Shall we?
是的，见鬼。
Yeah. Bloody hell.
我们就然他们从这儿过吧。
We'll just let him go here.
那么，继续。
Go on, then.
这也可能是它的一个站
This might be one of his stops.
好的
That's fine.
你认为我们，，，不。
Do you think we copped out there? No.
大多数重大事故都是和其他机动车
摆脱不了干系的
Most fatal accidents here
involve other vehicles.
路边的神龛表示了最危险的
转弯
Roadside shrines mark the
most dangerous corners,
司机和乘客所掉落悬崖的地方
where drivers and their passengers
have gone over the edge.
所以，我估计那些神龛之所以在那儿
So, I reckon those
shrines are there because
是因为他们曾经误判过转弯，不是吗
they'll just have misjudged
that bend, won't they?
哇
Wow.
你估计有多远？
How far down do you reckon that is?
哦，我们在1000，1200英尺处？够远了
Well, we're level with 1,000 feet...
12,000 feet? Far enough.
实际上有点恐怖
It's a bit scary actually.
你真的需要对这条路闭上眼，
什么都不想
You really do need to keep
your eyes on the road and
you don't think about that.
哦，我猜想那就是这里所发生过的事
Well, I'm assuming that's
what's happened here.
一辆车误判了转弯
A car has misjudged that bend.
稍微冷静点了，是吗？
Slightly sobering, isn't it?
真不是个令人愉快的念头
Not really a pleasant thought.
山崩的威胁是当下存在的危险
The threat of landslides
is an ever-present danger
在科马斯之路上
on the Comas road.
上百的立体方石可能从山腰横扫而至
Hundreds of cubic tonnes
of loose rock can
冲毁路经的一切
sweep down from the mountainside,
destroying everything in its path.
修路队为了使得道路开放使用进行
着一场持久战
Maintenance teams fight a constant
battle to keep the road open,
总会有个修路小队在路上的什么
地方随时行动
and there is always a team in
action somewhere on the road.
OK,所以，他们为我把道路开放了
20分钟
OK, so they've opened this road
for 20 minutes for us.
她说我们得走了
She's saying we've got to go.
她说无比路上当心
She said always go very carefully.
你明白吗？
Did you get that?
是的，看，当心，当心。
Yep. Look. Careful, careful.
我能通过吗？
Can I get past that?
还在往下吗？
还在往下。
It still coming down?
It's still coming down.
见鬼。
有东西下来了
Bloody hell.
There's stuff coming off.
实际上现在下来的飞快
It's actually coming
down quite fast now.
车上方的山坡不稳定，但是尽管如此，
The mountainside above the car is
unstable, but despite assurances,
前头的道路现在被封锁了。
the road ahead is now blocked.
我们不得不等等。
简直疯了，是不是？
We have to wait here for a sec.
It's crazy, isn't it?
他们只是说，他们打开过道路，有一个
起重机。
They just said they'd opened the road
and there's a bulldozer.
有一个硕大的起重机在装载一辆卡车。
There's a phenomenal digger
loading up a lorry.
我觉得我们的确过得去
I think we do just pass.
你微笑了吗？他点头了。
Did you smile? He nodded.
他点头的意思好像说,
“风险自负”
He nodded as if to say,
"Go at your own peril."
护路人员是一个重大五年计划项目成员
来重铺科马斯之路。
This road crew is part of
a major five-year
project to resurface the Comas road.
在丛林，它是一个链接各个孤立的山地社区到
市场集市的至关重要的锁链
It's a vital link that connects
the isolated mountain communities
to market towns in the jungle,
并且，所有的150公里的线路，在重铺之前，
需要被辗平，压平
and all 150 kilometres of the route
need to be scraped and compressed
before re-surfacing can begin.
谢谢！
Gracias.
这是一个交通拥堵。
Oh, here's a traffic jam.
他们好像蛮乐意在3500米工作，
They look very jolly
about working at 3,500 m,
在一条6或7英尺宽的路面上，
用一个硕大的挖掘机采石采土
quarrying earth on a road
about six or seven feet wide
with an enormous digger.
哇，看那儿
Woah, look at that.
所有的灰尘过来了。
All the dust coming off.
看上去真像是山的一部分倒下了
That really looked like part
of that hill was going fall...
以此同时，我们就在下面。
while we were under it.
在科马斯路上，6个小时之后，
他们到达了它的最高点，
海拔4589米
After six hours on the Comas road
they reach its highest point -
4,589 metres above sea level.
在这儿，司机们通常筋疲力尽，
视线模糊。
Drivers often suffer exhaustion
and blurred vision here.
在这样的高度，
人们有时候缺氧。
At this altitude,
people sometimes take oxygen.
什么，仅仅因为这个高度？
What, just because of the altitude?
是的，你觉得怎么样？
稍微有点头昏
Yeah. How you feeling?
Slightly drowsy.
你有症状了吧？不，我很好。
You got any symptoms? No, I'm fine.
我头疼了一会，
I've had a slight headache
for a while,
但是，我认为那是因为跟你在一块
的缘故
but I think that's
just being with you.
谢谢。好的。
Thanks. Yeah.
那么，那边的某个地方下去就是丛林
So, somewhere down there
is the jungle.
这使我有了无穷的力量。
That gives me
the feeling of enormous power.
是啊？
没有让你觉得...
Does it you?
Does it make you feel sort of...
是的.这相当的神奇.
我们在云之上了
Yeah. It's pretty amazing
we're above the clouds.
所以,从现在开始,我们奔向丛林,
然后深入丛林.
So from now on,
we're heading down into the jungle,
and then in the jungle
我们要找到康士城.
在80年代建成的那个城市.
we've got to find Constitucion.
Which was built in the '80s?
政府说他们要重迁首都
The government said they
would relocate the capital city
到这个秘鲁的理理位置的中心,
中心点,恰好也是丛林的中心.
to the geographical centre of Peru,
the middle point, which happens to
be in the middle of the jungle.
他们在巴西这么做了.
他们把首都搬到了一个人造的城市,
巴西利亚.
They did it in Brazil.
They moved the capital city to
a man-made one, Brasilia.
我认为大多数的首都城市都是人造的
我不想把你引导到这样的观点上来.
I think most capital cities
are man-made. I don't want
to pick you up on that point.
人工选址,
我们换个词语.
Artificially located,
let's change my wording.
但是在他们摆平科马斯之路之前
还有很长的路要走.
But there's a long way to go
before they get off the Comas road,
并且沉降在今天这样的时候尤其危险
and the descent is particularly
dangerous at this time of day.
我什么都看不见了.
你能看见东西吗?
I can't see anything at all.
Can you see anything?
我想走路.
I'll walk.
你能看见东西吗?
Can you see anything?
是的,我能看见...是的.我看到了一点路
在这儿.
Yeah, I can see... Yeah. I've got
a little bit of the road here.
我该走过去另一边吗?
我觉得现在还好,
我想告诉你,如果我...
Shall I walk up the other side?
I think I'm OK for now.
I'll tell you if I...
我从没感受过这么强烈的阳光直射到脸上
I've never had sun quite so strong
straight into the face.
如果我们再有一回陡峭的斜坡,
那么你可以出来
If we have another run of
sheer slope, then you can get out.
好的可视度在这儿是必须的,
因为我们在路上还有更多的困难要克服
Good visibility is essential here,
as there are still more
obstacles to overcome on the road.
恩,请原谅
Moo. Excuse us.
原谅我们
Excuse us.
那个出去了.
这个没有
That one's getting out the way.
This one isn't.
我要去放牧他们吗?
Shall I go and herd them?
HORN BEEPS
你所做的是,你在放另一只在路上.
What you've done there is,
you've put another one in the way.
你按了喇叭,现在没在路上的也到路上来了
You've honked, and now the one that
wasn't in the way is in the way.
出去,好吗.
Get out.. Right, OK. Hang on...
是的.这儿有个缺口
That's it. There's a gap.
谢谢,非常感谢.
Thank you, thank you very much.
简单,我们就像PROS
Easy! We're like pros.
ANCHOR奶油的商业宣传引导我相信,
牛会说话.
The Anchor butter commercials led me
to believe that cows could talk,
但是他们看起来似乎什么都不懂.
绝对不懂.
but they didn't seem
to understand anything. Not really.
在云之上行驶了一天之后,
After a day's drive
above the clouds,
小伙子们现在必须退回去到达亚马逊河
the boys must now drop back through
them to get to the Amazon basin.
这给了我们高空飞车幻觉,不是吗?
It does give the illusion
of driving into thin air, doesn't it?
高空飞车...
我可以唱这首歌
Driving in the air...
I could sing that for you.
"雪人"的曲调:
#我们飙车在高空...#
TO TUNE OF "THE SNOWMAN":
# We're driving in the air... #
不!
No!
在黄昏时分,一条几米高的悬崖显现
At dusk, visibility drops
to a few metres,
在12小时的路之后,
but after 12 hours on the road,
他们开车下来到塞提波,
找个过夜的地方.
they make it down to Satipo,
and a bed for the night.
本和修完成了亚马逊河
Ben and Hugh have made it
to the Amazon basin
现在必须向着秘鲁的中心雨林进发
and must now head further
into the rainforest
towards the centre of Peru
踏着他们寻找康士城之路
on their search
for the city of Constitucion.
但首先,他们需要商定到皮彻的路
But first, they need to negotiate
the road to Pichanaki,
那里的正午温度能高达40度
where temperatures can reach
40 degrees by midday.
啊!
Agh-yyah!
我就是想叫醒你.
I just wanted to wake you up.
实际上我挨沙地蚊子的叮咬一夜了
I've been bitten by sand flies,
actually.
脸上都是包
I've got them all over my face.
其实没那么痒.
一点也不痒,就我所见.
是不是很恶心?
They don't actually itch so much.
They don't itch at all, as far as
I can see. Are they nasty? Well,
哦,可能现在不该跟你说这些,
可是他们就是携带者相当恶心的病菌.
probably shouldn't tell you this now,
but they do carry
this rather nasty disease
那儿,他们叫做UTA,
回到英格兰,这被叫做leishmaniasis
that, out here, they call "uta",
and back in England
is called Leishmaniasis.
我不想知道这个。
I don't want to know.
你会好的，修
You'll be fine, Hugh.
秘鲁的亚马逊面积有100万平方公里
The Peruvian Amazon covers
nearly a million square kilometres.
上世纪过后，到这个地区的道路的数量
有了一个很大的增长。
Over the last century, there
has been a vast increase in
the number of roads into the area,
修路是为了来收割富饶的丛林植被财富
built to harvest the enormous
natural wealth of the jungle.
从塞提波到皮彻的路最初是由60年前
伐木工人修建的。
The road from Satipo to Pichanaki
was originally created
by loggers 60 years ago
现在主要被住在沿路的咖啡农民使用
but is now used primarily
by the coffee farmers
who live alongside it.
莉莉安娜经营着她的家族农场。
本地区最早的一个。
Liliana Palomino manages
her family's farm,
one of the oldest in this area.
她的父亲在50年代早去从高山地区
寻找田地而来
Her father arrived here from
the highlands in the early 1950s,
looking for land.
翻译：
TRANSLATION:
所以，她说她的父亲从科马斯来
我们也从那儿来。
So, she's saying that her father came
from Comas, where we've come from,
但是那时候没有我们所走的高速路
很宽的高速路！
but there was no big highway
like we just came on. VAST highway!
都是些小路。
很多都是河路，因为这里是原始雨林
It was small tracks.
A lot of it was river, because this
was virgin rainforest.
莉莉安娜的农场包括超过2000的咖啡
需要手工采收，
Liliana's farm contains
over 2,000 coffee plants which
need to be picked by hand,
这很可能是个危险的活。
and it can be risky work.
哦。OK!
Oh, OK!
那么，你们有几种蛇虫？
So, what kind of snakes do you have?
这可是一大长串名单！
This is becoming quite a long list!
我认为SHUSHUPE是丛林之王
I think "shushupe" is bushmaster.
丛林之王真恶心，是不是？是。
Bushmasters are nasty,
aren't they? Yep.
她大体上说，道路的好坏他们生活
方式的全部。
What she's basically said is,
the quality of the roads is integral
to their way of living,
因为，在这里，咖啡就是生命。
because coffee, here, is life.
所以，希望没有丛林之王回到路上
你需要向导吗？
So, hopefully no bushmasters on
our way back. Do you want to lead?
那很糟糕吗？
Was that bad?
本大笑
非常糟糕。哦。对不起
BEN LAUGHS
Quite bad, yeah. Sorry.
这毁了我们印第安纳琼斯的信用
That ruins my Indiana Jones
credibility there.
Not that I ever had any!
未经铺砌的皮彻的道路是去集市的
必经之地。
The unpaved Pichanaki road
is the only way for
locals to get to market,
在这条路线上事故频频
and there are frequent accidents
on this route.
看这个孩子
Look at this child.
有4个人在那儿。
有4个人在单车上。
There are four people on there.
There's four people on that bike,
那个孩子用一个类似围巾的什么
东西披裹着。
抓稳点
and that child has just got a...
like a...shawl wrapped around it,
holding it on.
谢谢。谢谢。
Gracias. Gracias.
你说西班牙语谢谢是期待四个人回应吗？
Do you say "gracias" because
you were expecting four back?
是的，我期待每个人...小心翼翼
Yeah, I was expecting each one to...
Check this out!
有个人，在后备箱！
哦，不，是不女士。太神奇了。
There is a man. In the boot!
Oh, no, a woman. Fantastic.
很搞笑。
他们所做的事，，，
That's very funny.
What they've done...
是个老太太，
他们被搁在车后面。
It's an old lady,
they've put in the back of the car!
他们把奶奶放在了后备箱。
They've put Grandma in the boot!
我们该同样的超过这辆卡车吗？是的
Shall we take over this truck
as well? Yeah.
你对此唯一能感到欣慰的是她没有被
捆绑在顶盖上。真的！
The only good thing you can say
about that is that she wasn't
strapped to a roof rack. True!
经过一个灰尘扑扑的5个小时的驾驶
之后，他们到达了皮彻。
After a dusty five-hour drive,
they reach Pichanaki,
一个买咖啡橘子水果的繁忙集市。
a busy town where coffee and citrus
fruits and are brought to market.
不确定这个卡车是干嘛的。它要左转了，
我认为，由转向灯看出。
Not quite sure what this truck's
doing. It's turning left,
I think, by the indicator.
哦，我在丛林里太久了，我几乎要
得城市综合症了。
Oh... I've been in the jungle for so
long, I'm almost getting urban shock.
这条路被修建于60年代来刺激移民从
山地来此。
This road was built in the 1960s to
encourage migration
from the highlands,
现在它是在秘鲁丛林里最繁忙
的地方之一了。
and it's now one of the busiest
in the Peruvian jungle.
大量的这些小马力出租车之类的。
Lots of these little
motor taxi things.
这些三轮车之类的？
似乎有相当多。
有上千辆。
These three-wheel drive things?
There seems to be quite a lot.
There are thousands of them.
当道路延伸到皮彻这里的时候，
是一个300人的村庄。
When the road arrived in Pichanaki,
it was a village of 300 people
周围地区住满了土著部落。
and the surrounding area was
populated by indigenous tribes.
今天，这些部落经受着流入到此
的6000外来常驻人口的挤压。
Today, those tribes have been
pushed out by an influx
of over 60,000 settlers.
本和修在进一步向雨林，
秘鲁的中心，
进发之前在此过夜
Ben and Hugh stay the night here
before heading further
into the rainforest
and the centre of Peru.
为了到达那儿，他们首先要经过
山里的丛林到波祖城
To get there, they first
have to drive the
mountain jungle road to Pozuzo,
这个城市依傍着险峻的皮彻河
which runs alongside
the dangerous Pichanaki River.
我打赌冬天时雨季
I bet in the winter,
when it's rainy season,
这个一定会充满
this must just fill up.
皮彻，亚马逊强大属地
The Pichanaki, a powerful tributary
of the Amazon,
能升高4米，在当下这个水平上
can rise four metres
above its current level.
道路的整个断面有规律的被冲刷掉
Whole sections of this road are
regularly washed away,
这就是几次重大事故的情景
and it's been the scene of several
fatal accidents.
看见这一点了吗？这看起来像被诅咒
的什么东西。
See this bit here? That looks like
it's been blasted, or something.
它这儿有一些直线。
摩擦的痕迹。那么是怎么回事呢?
It's got these lines in it.
Scrape marks. So what are they?
护路对在进行着一场无望的战争
Maintenance teams are fighting
a desperate battle
从塌陷的河床把道路转移并保持
道路通行。
to move the road away from the
collapsing riverbank
and keep it open to traffic.
这的确看起来像他们LAY什么东西在那儿
是不是呀？
It does look they're laying something
up there, doesn't it?
他们打开了一些什么线圈
他们在管子里粘了东西。
这些家伙，
They're uncoiling something.
They're sticking things in tubes.
This bloke here,
我认为他们放进去了一个管子
并且他弄了一个棍棒
I think they've put a tube in
and he's got a stick
and he's ramming...charge, I guess.
如果他们打算引爆那个，
我们将有一个极度
If they are going to blow that up,
we're going to have an
extraordinary...
长久的等待？坐下来看看风景。
Long wait? ..seating view.
这就是我们之间的不同。
我真的很激动。
你在担心交通阻塞
That's the difference between us.
I'm really excited,
you're worried about the traffic jam!
对于本不幸的是，
首席工程师哈罗德
Unfortunately for Ben,
chief engineer Harold Abad
想要所有的机动车离开道路
在爆破开始之前。
wants all vehicles to clear the road
before blasting begins.
海，我是修
海，我是哈罗德。
我是本
你讲英语吗？
多少会一点。
Hi, I'm Hugh. Hi, Harold.
I'm Ben. You speak English?
More or less.
你们怎么清掉那个石头？
钻一个孔？
是的。
放炸药进去？
How do you clear that rock?
Drill a hole? Yeah. Put dynamite in?
是的，我们有一个孔，或许3米
Yeah, we have a hole
maybe three metres...
放一些TNT和爆炸物。
现在他们正在这么做吗？
put some TNT...and explosions.
And that's what they're doing now?
是的。
Yeah.
你工作在炸药和山崩的环境下，
这一定是非常危险的工作吧？
是的，
You're working with dynamite
and landslides, that must be very
dangerous work? Yeah,
因为这里，不是多牢固，这个地方，
because here, it's not
exactly strong, this part.
举例来说，昨天，我们正工作，
For example, yesterday,
we were working
我们遇到了非常非常大的岩石滚下来。
and we have, coming down,
very, very big rocks,
去年，我们有一个人因为这个情况死了
and the last year, we have
one people die for that reason.
别岩石压死？
是的，他死了，过世了
Hit by a rock?
Yeah, he died, he pass away.
所以对我们来说在这条路上最危险的时候
可能会是他们爆破的时候？啊。
So the most dangerous time
for us to be on this road would be
when they blow it up? Uh-huh.
所以我们需要远离这条路？
啊。
So we need to get out of the way?
Uh-huh.
我们要走了。好的。再见。
再见，再见
We'll get going. OK. See you. Bye.
Bye. See you.
车被交通阻塞了2个小时了已经
The car's been stuck in traffic
for two hours now,
仍然有另外的30公里的道路工作
要进行。
and there's still another
30km of roadworks to get through.
他们鸣笛
They honked.
喇叭声
HORN BEEPS
很好的鸣笛，
我注意到他们那么做了
That's a good honk,
I've noticed they do that here.
你已经变得像我妻子了。
你靠过去。
You've become like my wife,
you lean across.
侵犯了你的私人地盘了吗？
是的
Was that encroaching on your
personal space? Yeah.
我变得更熟稔了没有
是的。嗯。
Am I becoming too over-familiar?
Yes, hmm.
我总是其他的司机们非常关心
I've always been most concerned
about other drivers -
我不是说的修=但是我一会回来
and I don't necessarily mean Hugh -
but I'll get
back to that in a second.
哇，别
刮擦声
Whoa! Try not to...
SCRAPING
我不想
不，不，我意思是，我怎么能
避免那个呢？
I won't bottom out the car.
No, no. I mean, how could I have
avoided that?
修和我已经在车里几天了。
我感觉信心满满。
Hugh and I have been in a car
for a few days now,
and I'm feeling confident,
但是地形变化了，
所以在山里信心满满是另外一回事
but the terrain has changed,
so it's one thing feeling confident
up in the mountains,
在丛林里是既然不同的。
it's different in the jungle.
现在不要再走了。那辆卡车已经
挨的尽可能的近了。
Don't go more to the right now. That
truck is close enough as it is.
本在他跟人们道谢的时候做了这件事
Ben does this thing whereby he says
thank you to people...
人们显然听不见他的话，他们
在几英里之外。
who obviously can't hear him,
who are miles away.
我认为如果你再往右一点，，，谢谢
I think if you had gone
more to the right... Gracias!
嗯，如果我再往右一点？
Hmm. If I'd gone more to the right?
而不是往，，，他会说，谢谢
Rather than just going...
he will actually go, "Thank you!"
我们将会被卡在这辆卡车的后面整天？
你想让我超车？
Are we going to be stuck behind
this truck for the whole way?
You want me to overtake?
哦，，，他想让我超车。
是的。他做了。走，走，，，，
Well... He wants me to overtake.
Yeah, he does. Go, go, go, go, go.
我只是说说。
I was just chatting.
谢谢
Gracias.
走，嘿，看，现在，你已经把自己
在右边了。
你打算做什么？
Go. Hey, look, now. Now you've
got yourself in a right pickle.
What are you going to do?
我打算避开这辆货车并且打算避开面包车
你是不是打算切碎他？
I'm going to avoid the lorry
and I'm going to avoid the minibus.
Weren't you just cutting him up?
面包车，看，干得好。
The minibus. Look. Well done.
本和修现在一路灰尘地，
已经到达了H峡谷
Ben and Hugh have now reached
the Huancabamba canyon and the dirt
track which runs alongside it.
这是一条众所周知的情况多变的路
It's a notoriously unstable road
有着300米的悬崖通向下方的河
with drops of over 300 metres
into the river below.
我认为这是我们遇见过的最崎岖的一段。
I think this is the bumpiest section
we've been on. Yes.
你觉得以15英里的时速有可能
WHIPLASH?
我认为如此。
Is it possible to get whiplash
at 15 miles an hour? I think so.
稳住。
Steady...
这儿是峡谷的最高点
This is the highest point
of the canyon,
即将面临的路况是一个真正的危险
and oncoming traffic is
a real danger.
在2009,2名游客从这条路上滚落
In 2009, two tourists veered
off the road here
在下方的山谷里丢掉了性命
and plunged to their deaths
in the valley below.
不约而同:噢！
BOTH: Ohhh-ohhh!
在这停下？
他让我们过去那边
Stop here?
He wants us to go over here.
他让我们过去吗？
我不知道。
Does he want us to go over here?
I don't know.
这是一个单行道，卡车不打算让路
It's a single-track road
and the trucks aren't giving way.
我应该过去吗
Shall I go into there?
哦，我太靠近了。
Oh, blimey. How close am I?
空间足够大吗？
Is that enough room?
看看这儿的悬崖
Look at this drop here.
他相当的顽固，是不是？
He was fairly insistent, wasn't he?
他不想我们过去。好像说，
“你打算过去，伙计”
He didn't want us to go there. That
was like, "You're going there, mate."
我认为打滑的厉害
I thought that was quite slick.
你认为他们会不会说，
我们不是附近的人
Do you think they could tell
we weren't from around here?
那是什么？威尔克。
What's that? Wilkommen.
威尔克在，，，那说的是什么？
Wilkommen in... What does that say?
波祖
Pozuzo.
(西语）
你能翻译那么吗？
Einzigen Osterriechisch Deutschen
kolonie der welt.
Can you translate that?
欢迎来波祖
全世界唯一的奥地利德国殖民地
Welcome to Pozuzo -
the only Austrian, German colony...
1859，很奇怪
in the world. 1859. This is weird.
很奇怪
This is weird.
看起来我们到达了一个奥地利村庄
It looks like we have arrived
in an Austrian village.
非常的没有秘鲁味儿
This is so un-Peruvian.
像个滑雪胜地，不是吗？
It's like a ski resort, isn't it?
丛林滑雪胜地
A ski resort in the jungle.
同样的，难以置信的宜人，不是吗？
It's incredibly neat
as well, isn't it?
有点怪怪的，像个微缩城，不是吗？
This is a bit freaky, it's
a bit like a toy town, isn't it?
看上去很德国味儿-那个人看起来
很德国味儿
He looks German -
that man looked German.
哪儿？那儿。看他多高大！
Where? There. Look how tall he is!
沉迷于民俗老一套对我来说非常危险
There is a very, very great danger
of me starting to indulge in
national stereotyping.
究竟为什么这儿会有这么一个地方的？
How on earth
did a place like this get here?
那是我也没法理解的。
That's what I don't understand.
波祖仍然居住着中19世界移民过来的
欧洲人后裔
Pozuzo is still inhabited
by the descendants of the
European settlers, who arrived
here in the mid 19th century.
就像本地约瑟居民一样。
Like local resident Jose Castrada.
我们注意到在丛林中部的广场中间
有个巨轮
We can't help but notice there is an
enormous ship in the middle
of the square -
这个究竟干吗出现这儿的？
in the middle of the jungle
here. What on earth is this here?
故事开始于1850,
The story began
政府曾在秘鲁这里寻求丛林中心
地带的殖民拓展
in 1850. The Government here
in Peru pursued the idea of
colonising the central jungle.
334人从安特卫普登船-一部分是
奥地利人，一部分是德国人。
334 people board in Antwerp -
a part of them were Austrians
and a part of them were Germans.
所以，你能告诉我们一些航行的
情况吗？花了多久时间？
So, can you tell us a bit about the
boat journey and how long it took?
大约4个月从安特卫普来到这里
It took about four months
to come here from Antwerp.
是一个GUANO船-配给了水，
食物，一切
It was a guano ship -
they ration the water, they
ration the food and everything.
我认为6人死了。所以，船上发生
过相当悲惨的事
I think six people died there. So,
pretty miserable existence on board.
当然
Of course.
他们在秘鲁的这个地方登陆，
跋涉了2年多来到这儿
They landed here in Peru
and they hiked more than two years
to come here.
从这儿到这儿花了他们2年的时间？
It took them two years
to get from the coast...?
是的。从这里的海岸
Yeah, from the coast here.
离波祖只有180
Only 180 came here to Pozuzo.
那么，失踪的150人怎样了？
So, what happened to
that missing 150 or so?
很多放弃了，很多死在途中
Lots of them gave up
and lots of them died on the way.
病死吗？
Died from disease?
病死，饿死，冻死，等等
From disease, from hunger,
cold and so on.
那么，他们到这儿的时候期待
什么结果？
So, what were they
expecting when they got here?
他们是不是认为原本应该有建筑
和道路？他们被保证过什么承诺？
Did they think there would
be buildings and roads,
what were they promised?
没有，他们期待有田地，有
一条路通往首都
No, they was expecting to
have land and to have
a road connection to the capital.
其实没有？
没有。
Which they didn't?
They didn't.
那么，这条路什么时候终于修到这儿的？
So when did the road finally arrive?
哦，被隔绝之后的100年，1975年
Well, after 100 years of isolation,
in 1975,
这条路第一次修到波祖这儿
the road arrived here in Pozuzo
for the first time.
随着道路通到这儿的还有新东西，
新材料，新通讯。
And with the road came
also the new things - new materials,
new communications.
还有财富？还有财富
And wealth? And wealth also.
约瑟，谢谢你。谢谢。
Jose, thank you very much. Thank you.
西语
Auf Wiedersehn. Auf Wiedersehn.
自从路修道这儿，波祖就繁荣起来
Pozuzo has thrived since
the arrival of the road
但是它保持了欧洲的根和骄傲，
依然能受到德国和奥地利的财政
支持
but it remains proud of its European
roots and still receives financial
support from Germany and Austria.
旅程的下一个阶段是找到康士城，
从波祖出发，横穿恐怖
The next stage of the journey to
find the city of Constitucion,
runs from Pozuzo across the fearsome
的H峡谷，到C镇
Huancabamba Canyon,
to the town of Codo.
但是首先，他们需要更换车辆，
因为前方的路普通的4*4驱不动
But first they need to change their
vehicle, as the road ahead can't
be driven in an ordinary 4x4.
这家车行出租有着高车盘
的PICK-UP卡车，
This garage rents pick-up trucks
with higher ground clearance
以对付最具挑战性的丛林小径
to cope with the most
challenging jungle tracks.
这就是我们的车了。
我认为如此。（西语）
So this must be our car.
I think so, Hola, senor.
他们说西班牙语
THEY SPEAK SPANISH
他说，这就是我们在这种路上
所需要的车
So he said, this is the car
we wanted for the route.
让我们四处观察一下。
你踢那个干吗？
Let's have a look around.
Why do you kick that?
大家都这么做
我看见过。
你知道踢了就有好处
It's what everyone does.
I've seen them. You kick it
and it makes it look good.
尽管你不知道为什么。
我检查一下后边
You have no idea what it's for
though. I'm going to check the back.
很棒，我们之一可以骑在顶上
This is great, one of us
can ride up in the top here.
那对我很好。我开车，你呆在那儿
That's fine by me, I'll drive
you stay up there.
你不觉得太自大了吗？
Do you think it'll be bouncy?
哦！
Oooh!
从波祖出来的路交叉了若干条
急落入河的急流，
The road out of Pozuzo is
crossed by several streams,
which cascade into
the river below,
使得路面不可预测，并易于塌陷
making the road-surface
unpredictable and prone to collapse.
哦，当地人说这是即将面临的
最大的困难
Well, the locals say that this
is one of
the hardest parts that's coming up.
实际上，我第一次觉得有一点紧张。
I'm actually, for the first time,
feeling a little bit nervous.
看这个!
Look at this!
路通往哪里？
Where does the road go?
路在哪里？
Where is the road?
我认为路曾经一度通往那里
I think the road used to go there.
穿过那儿？
那儿一定是路
Across there?
That must be the road there.
抱歉，你看不见，是不是？
Sorry, you couldn't
really see it, could you?
你看好路
You keep your eyes on the road,
或者说看好小径或者看准了泥巴路，
随便我们怎么称呼它吧。
or one the track or on the
mud, whatever we call it.
我的确认为你应该在这个点上仔细点
I do think you should be
careful at this bit here.
因为直行？
Because it's straight on?
哦，因为我可以看到那儿有直行标记
并且看起来已经有某个人这么做了
Well,
because I can see there are marks
that go straight on and it looks
like someone's done that already.
有，是不是有？
这是人们刹车的地方。
There are, aren't there?
This is where people skid off.
这些轮胎的痕迹刚好经过了边缘
Those tyre tracks go
right over the edge.
那边一辆车也没有，是不是？
There's not a car over
there, is there?
哦，偶的神！
Oh, Lord!
简直疯了
This is mad.
这不是路
This is not a road.
本和修距离秘鲁中心仍然还有350公里
Ben and Hugh are still
350 kilometres away from the centre
被选为康士城新首都的场所
of Peru and the site chosen for
the new capital of Constitucion.
你认为我们能找到这个地方吗？
Do you think we'll find this place?
我担心的事是我们没在地图上
I find it a bit worrying
that it's not on our map
见过它，只是有人听说过它
that we were looking at but
other people have heard of it.
有人听说过它。
它在八十年代被修建。
Some people have heard of it.
It was only built in the 1980s.
哦，我们甚至不知道它被建到什么程度
Well, we don't
even know how much of it was built.
我们越我前走，我越觉得这个新手段的
念头越荒唐。
And the further we go,
the more ridiculous I think
this idea of a new capital is.
他们现在不得不过河到达CODO的城镇
They now have to cross the
river to reach the town of Codo.
一条新的双行道大桥正在施工，
但不幸的是得有个几周才能开放通行
A brand new two-lane bridge is under
construction but unfortunately it
doesn't open for another few weeks.
他们就不得不从老桥过，
老桥正准备拆除
They will have to use the old
bridge, which is currently
being prepared for demolition.
哦，见鬼！
Oh, bloody hell.
不不！看那个！
No way! Look at that!
哦，上帝！
Oh, my God!
当他们接近桥下的时候，
修很担心刹车制动器
As they approach the bridge,
Hugh is worried about the brakes.
感觉怎么样？
How does that feel?
应该没事，只要我能停下车
Should be all right,
as long as I can stop it.
哦，就是这样，你能行吗？
要不要试试这里。哦。现在我可以了
Well, that's the thing, can you? Do
you want to try here. Oh, I can now.
你可以了吗？一定能停下吗？
You can? Definitely stop?
我们打算，，，认真的说，我们打算
径直通过那个边缘
We're going... I'm serious though
we will go straight over that edge.
盯紧了，，，
Look at this tight...
你得怎么转过去
You've got to somehow turn here.
你得做到一个无比高分的转向
You're going to have to
do a zillion point turn.
我一点都没就绪
I'm not in any gear.
挂离合
Push the clutch.
以便从低回到高，现在你可以就绪了吗？
That's low so that should be back
into high, so can you get a gear now?
你在倒车吗？我不想倒车，我想前进
Are you into reverse? I don't
want reverse, I want to go forward.
你现在应该能了，好的
You should be able to now, OK.
OK,OK,原来越近了
OK, OK, that's probably close.
你需要我出来在那边指方向吗？
是的
Do you want me to actually get
out and point you over here?
Yeah.
西语
Hola, senor.
把她拉一边去。
Pull her round this way.
他们说西班牙。
THEY SPEAK SPANISH
她说这很安全
He said it's safe.
转，继续转
Turning, turning more.
你有了很大的空间，
修，大得多的空间
You've got lots of room here,
Hugh, lots more room.
是的，但这边没有
Yeah, but none here.
我得回去，我做不到，我得回去
I've got to go back, I can't
do that. I've got to go back.
皮卡紧紧的靠着支撑大桥的一根
柱子上
The pick-up is pressing
against one of the pillars
holding the bridge up.
现在工程师说
And now the engineer is concerned.
他说西语
HE SPEAKS SPANISH
哇
Whoa!
你还好吗？
You OK?
我得回去
I've got to go back.
打方向盘，
继续打，
Turn the wheels around,
turn the wheels more,
再转，接着转
turn them more, turn the wheels more.
是的，是的，很好
Yeah, yeah, that's good.
引擎转数
ENGINE REVS
开始转，再转，
Start turning, turning more. Full on.
现在往这一边打方向
Now turn the wheels
over to this side here.
OK.
THEY SPEAK SPANISH
你还没有穿过大桥这一点是最可怕的
We're not even across the bridge
yet and that's the most terrifying
bit of it.
难以置信。
我们还没下来
This is unbelievable.
We're not off it yet.
那边怎么样了？
How am I doing on that side?
你有了很多空隙了
You've got lots of room.
当你说很多空隙，，，
很多。戈登！
When you say loads of room...
Lots. Gordon Bennett!
看开点。你能感到吗？
Look at it bouncing. Can you feel it?
是的，不哟着急，我现在走得很慢
Yeah, don't worry,
I'm going very slowly now.
哇!我要跳起来了
Woo hoo! I'm going to jump.
看一下，难以置信。
我打算出来，看一下
Have a look, that is unbelievable.
I'm gonna get out
and have a look at that.
是的，那是一座可怕的桥要通过
Yeah, that was a terrifying
bridge to go across.
当他打方向的时候，他们在进入WIRE,
实际上挂在了桥上
When he was turning his wheels, they
were going into the wire and actually
hanging over the bridge.
你留了多少汗？很多。
How much did you sweat? Quite a lot.
你也要感受一下吗？
一点也不想
Do you want to feel that?
Not really.
我在操作，本在指引，
所以我如果撞到柱子，至少40%
是他的错
I was steering, Ben was guiding,
so the fact I hit the pillar
is at least 40% his fault.
那么，没有卡车能通过那儿，是不是？
So, no truck can get across there,
can it?
我们今天看见2辆卡车了
We have seen two trucks today.
他们都没有通过去，是不是？
They can't have come
across that, can they?
这是“BIEN DANADO”
It was "bien danado",
意思是徒劳无功，
像一个工人所说的，
好像我们往后倒退了
which means well damaged,
as one of the workmen said as we
drove past afterwards.
我对修隐瞒了这个秘密。
我认为他有一点
I kept that secret from Hugh.
I think he was a bit...
我觉得他有一点受打击
I think he felt a bit dented himself.
我们应该继续吗？是的，我们来吧
Shall we carry on? Yeah, let's.
我觉得，我早早就会得心脏病。
你能开车吗？
I thought I was going
to have a heart attack earlier.
Can you drive?
我能开车吗？
Can I drive?
搞清楚这座桥花了几个钟头，
他们不得不抹黑赶完到CODO的剩下的路
It's taken an hour to clear the
bridge and they have to drive
the rest of the road in the dark
before reaching Codo,
where they can plan the route ahead.
这最后的一点
This last bit.
我们在H峡谷了，你知道吗？
We were in the Canyon of the
Huancas, did you know that?
现在，我们从这儿上去，
然后这里的某个地方
And now we go up here
and then somewhere in here...
就是康士城
is Constitucion...
相当可怕的事情是，这儿也没有路，
and what's rather alarming
about it is there is no road
也没有路标，更甚的，没有这座
迷失之城的线索
or road marks. And, more notably,
no mention of the lost city.
我们得找到它。
哦，应该会很容易
And we've got to find it.
Well, that should be easy.
本和修现在已经进入了他们旅程
的最后阶段
Ben and Hugh have now reached
the final stage of their journey.
康士城传闻位于秘鲁的地理中心位置
Constitucion reportedly lies at
the geographical centre of Peru.
要到达那儿，他们必须离开河谷，
To get there, they must leave
the river valley,
然后穿过沼泽，向着丛林中心驶去
then drive across swampland
into the heart of the jungle.
但是峡谷还有一个最后的可怕的
爬坡要克服
But the canyon has one
final terrifying climb to negotiate.
现在是上午很早的时候
It's too early
in the morning for this.
这么狭窄。我能说，我看不见那儿没有
悬崖吗？
This is so narrow. Can I say, I
can't see where the drop is there?
尽可能的靠近那边，我能搞定那个
悬崖吗？
Keep as close to that side as
you can. Am I OK with that drop?
哦，上帝，我觉得我挂在这边了。
Oh, my God, I feel like I'm
actually hanging over the side.
皮卡被陷在了峻峭的岩石和湍流的
卡班巴河之间。
The pick-up is trapped
between a sheer rock-face and
the fast-flowing Huancabamba river.
对，现在穿过去吧。
过去。
Right, get over there now.
Get over there.
还有一点。
There's another bit.
尽可能的靠近那一边
Close to that side as you can now.
杀了我吧。
Bugger me.
告诉我多远。尽可能的靠近那堵墙
Tell me how far. Just stay as
close as you can to that wall.
不要担心这一边，只要你尽可能的
保持靠近
Don't worry about this side but
if you keep as close as you can...
我看不见那一边
过去，过去，
那儿，过去
I can't see that side.
Get over there, get over
there, get over there.
这太荒唐了
This is ridiculous.
如果我撞上石头，
我会弹进去
If I hit the rock,
I'll bounce back in.
哦，那就不要撞上石头
Well, don't hit the rock then.
他们终于搞清了河谷并靠近了
秘鲁中心
They have finally cleared
the river valley
and are close to the centre of Peru.
这条路的这个路段才修建了几年而已，
This section of the road was only
built a few years ago but already
但对当地环境已经产生了巨大的影响
has had a huge impact
on the local environment.
非法砍伐已经砍出来大片的雨林空地
Illegal tree felling has cleared
vast areas of rainforest
非法放牧也使得丛林不能再恢复
and cattle farming ensures that
the jungle cannot grow back.
在地图上，我们位于丛林的中心位置
On the map, we are in the middle
你记得所看到过的这一点吗？
of the jungle,
do you remember looking at that?
没有路，周围什么也没有
There was no roads - nothing around.
这里本应该是繁茂的原始森林
So this should be thick,
primary jungle.
看看我们周围
And look around us.
我猜这条路基本上被用来运送
木材了，不是吗？
I guess this road mostly is
just used to take wood, isn't it?
运送原木。
看看这些树-好大的树
Take logs.
See these trees here - the big ones.
尽管这些只是他们砍剩下的。
It looks to me as though they're
the ones that have been left.
他们砍伐了大片区域的树木，不是吗？
They've cleared massive
areas of trees, haven't they?
这些道路往雨林深处延伸越多，
The further these roads
encroach into the rainforest,
他们打算开发的自然资源就越多
the more the natural resources
they're going to be exploiting.
这地方可能会是濒临灭绝的首个风景
之一
This could be one of the first
landscapes that becomes extinct.
距离本和修路程的终点现在只有75KM
The end of Ben and Hugh's journey
is now only 75 kilometres away.
但是这条路最后的这段路2年前才
刚刚修完，甚至不曾出现在地图上过
But this final stage of the road
was only completed two years ago
and doesn't even appear on the map.
只是像MUD路一样的仅仅被当地人所知
It's known to locals
simply as the Mud Road.
这是条不错的路，是不是呀
This is a good road, isn't it?
好的，那么，现在，我们想要到
这个里边去。
OK, so now we want to go
into this one over here -
从右边出来
so out to the right.
我被陷住了
I'm stuck.
现在，先进去，如果你绕着右边一点
拉出来
Now into first and if you pull it
around to the right a little bit...
他们才走了3公里，但是他们已经陷住了
They have only gone three kilometres
but they are already stuck.
打转了，打转了。
It's spinning, spinning.
你想干什么，修，你弄了些干燥的
东西上来，是的，的确
What you want to do, Hugh,
you've got some drier stuff
up here, yeah, exactly.
好，满满来，
Nice, slow tread...
我们正要回到洞里了。我得回去
We're going to go back into
that hole. I've got to go back.
如果皮卡不能穿过泥巴，他们就麻烦了
If the pick-up can't get through
the mud, they are trouble.
在丛林中间可没有什么救援服务
There are no rescue services
in the middle of the jungle.
如果你右打方向，
If you turn the wheels right...
我不知道你能不能得到足够的牵引力
I don't know
if you can get enough traction.
这正要把我送回到那个洞里面
It's going to
send me back into that hole.
啊，差一点了
Agh, so nearly.
我们所需要做的事是尽量得到牵引力
并指向那个方向-那条路
What we want to do is try
and get traction up
pointing into the jungle - that way.
这才是我们所需要尝试做的事
有个小斜坡，是的，满满来，是的
It's what we want to try and do.
There's a bit of a slope, yeah.
Nice slow traction, yeah.
走，走，，，，，
Go, go, go, go, go...
继续走，继续走，
Keep going, keep going!
好的，现在在哪儿了？
Yes! Now where?
进来了。径直往那儿。是的。
Into here. Straight on there. Yep.
进来一点
Into this bit.
先不要乐
Don't smile yet.
我们还有50英里呢。
We've still got another 50 miles.
这个嘛!我知道。
Of this! I know.
其他的车辆稀少而远离，在MUN路上
Other vehicles are few and
far between on the Mud Road.
这个属于约瑟的-一个当地的市长，为这
一区域的道路负责的官员
This one belongs to Jose Caballero -
a local mayor and the official
responsible for roads in this area.
那么，谁修了这条路？
So who built this road?
他修的
He built it.
我是说，为了我们。
I'm saying, for us,
有一点困难。
it's a little bit difficult.
他说，在他们这儿的冬季，
这个是封路的，这一时期能通行吗？
What he's saying is,
in their winter, this is impassable.
At the moment this is good?
这是条很棒的路，如果我们被
陷住会怎样？
This is a great road.
What happens if we get stuck?
关键的事情是跟另一辆车一起赶路，
并确保能有个绳子把其中一个拖出来。
The key is to go with another vehicle
and make sure they've got
ropes to pull one out.
没有机动车接待处在这里，什么都没有
No mobile reception or anything here.
你愿意跟我们同行吗？
Would you like to come with us?
我说，开个玩笑。
I said it's a joke.
我认为他当真了。
我们也当真了，不是吗，某种程度上
I think he was taking you seriously,
although we are being serious,
aren't we, in a kind of way?
本已经翻越了MUD路的最后路段，
他们希望沿着这段路达到康士城
Ben has taken over for the final
section of the Mud Road, which
they hope leads to Constitucion.
甚至经验丰富的本地司机也会
在这儿陷住。
Even experienced local
drivers get bogged down here.
从这一边穿过，你认为呢？
Cross over to this
side, do you think?
是的，那一边似乎用过了
Yeah, and that side
seems to be used.
只要它不把我们带到树上去
As long as it doesn't
take us into that tree.
我可以加在你的辙痕上。
I could add to your dent.
我们弄的辙痕，我得同意。
WE made that dent! I have to agree.
哇，TMD！
Whoa, fucking hell!
观众们请原谅。
Pardon me, viewers.
这条路的最后几公里完全掉到
水里去了。
The last kilometre of this road
is completely submerged
但小伙子们终于挂着泥巴继续前行了。
but the boys are finally
getting the hang of mud driving.
这个是从窗户里进来的
It's coming in through the window.
你在做什么？
我只是沿着这条小径
What are you doing?
I'm just following the tracks.
哦，太神奇了。每次你认为玩完的时候
都没玩完。
Oh, that's fantastic. Every time
you think it's over, it's not over.
直到那个胖女士唱的时候才完。见鬼
It's not over till the fat woman
sings. Bloody hell!
真漂亮！
Beautiful!
走，走，，，，佛格！
Go, go, go. Go, Fogle!
走，走！
Go, go!
干得好，伙计，那太给力了
Well done, mate. That was fantastic.
是的。
Yes!
他们到达了一个小小的灰尘很大的城镇，
这个镇出现在80年代，以招待来此建筑
They have arrived in a small
dirt town that emerged in
the 1980s to house and feed
康士城的员工们的食宿
construction crews who came to
build the city of Constitucion.
为了揭秘这个新秘鲁首都之梦的究竟
To discover what happened to the
dream of a new Peruvian capital,
本和修来到了一个当地政府的办公室。
Ben and Hugh have come to
a local government office...
哦，戴维德！
Ah, David!
戴维德是一个导游和历史学家
..Where David Zevallos
is a guide and historian.
这是我们的前总统佛那多。
This is our ex-president,
Fernando Belaunde Terry.
他对我们来说是个非常重要的人，
他决定在丛林中间修建康士城，
He was a very important man for us
and he decided to build Constitucion
city in the middle of the jungle.
那么它打算建多大呢？
And how big was it going to be?
曾打算建成一个大城市，打算作为秘鲁的首都
It was going to be a big city. It
was going to be the capital of Peru.
你在这儿可以看见这个规划。
Here you can see the plans here.
这里我们有市民中心，商业中心，
Here we have the civic centre,
the commercial centre,
他打算为我们的市民建立这样的房屋
看看这个！
houses that he wanted to build like
this for our citizens. Look at that!
这是个宏大的工程，不是吗？
That is a massive project, isn't it?
看看这条路的数字！看上去像是条3行道
的高速公路
Look at the size of that road! That
looks like a triple-lane highway.
那么，为什么他要选择这个地方作为新
首都的地点呢
So, why did he choose here as
the location for the new capital?
他认为这个地方有战略意义
He thought it was a strategic place.
战略意义？
传略意义。
A strategic place? A strategic place.
是的，它在丛林的中心。
Yeah, it was the
centre of the jungle.
它很重要，但它最终什么也没有。
因为我们无法完成它
It was important
but it was nothing at the end,
because we couldn't finish that.
那么，到底出了什么状况？
So what went wrong?
哦，有太多的腐败
Well, there was a lot of corruption.
太多的人贪污钱财。
There was a lot of
people robbing money.
你对于这个状况没能解决而失望吗？
是的，当然。
Are you disappointed that this never
got off the ground? Yes, of course.
作为一个秘鲁人，
我对此很失望，因为很多人将会
在这里生活
As a Peruvian citizen,
I am disappointed for that because a
lot of people would be living there.
现在，它只是被遗忘在了丛林中间。
And now it's just forgotten in
the middle of the jungle.
但是你可以再这条路的尽头看见它
But you can see it at
the end of the road.
我们能看见这条路通往哪儿吗？
We can see where
this was going to be?
是的，它会出现在路的尽头。
Yes, it was going to be
at the end of the road.
谢谢。
Thanks very much. Muchos gracias.
不客气
You're welcome.
选为新首都的地址似乎在3KM之外。
The site chosen for the new capital
lies three kilometres away,
在秘鲁的地理位置正中心
at the exact geographical centre
of Peru.
B总统的远大理想是有一条贯穿丛林
的大道，通往新的城市
President Belaunde Terry's grand
vision was for a huge road through
the jungle, leading to the new city.
上千的土著人为此项目从他们的故土
搬迁来此
Thousands of indigenous
people were moved from
their land in preparation.
但是，今天，除了这条路，基本什么
都没剩下。
But, today,
little but the road remains.
那么，这条路也许就是全部了，我猜，
不是吗？
So, this would have all been
part of it, I guess, wouldn't it?
我们所行走的这条路也许就是那些规划的全部，
不是吗？
This road we're on now would have all
been part of those plans, isn't it?
那么，这个也许就像字面上说的，路的尽头
So this might be - literally -
the end of the road.
你其实不常得出那种观点
It's not often
you actually find that point.
那么，这其实是康士城所剩余的东西
So this is effectively what's left
of the city of Constitucion.
一个新城市仅仅在建了几栋房子
之后就被遗弃了，
The new city was abandoned
after only a few houses were built,
但是这里现在居住的是爱莎人-秘鲁
最大的土著部落
but it is now inhabited by members
of the Ashaninka people - the
largest indigenous tribe in Peru.
部落首领是72岁的艾丽西亚
The community is led by
72-year-old Alicia Arellano.
本说西班牙语
BEN SPEAKS SPANISH
艾丽西亚
Alicia.
修
Hugh.
那么，她已经在这里生活了23年了。
So she's been here for 23 years.
他们的B总统修建了这些建筑给他们居住
So that's President Belaunde created
these buildings they moved into.
他们不得不清扫全部，不得不再次返回丛林
So they had to clean it all. They
had to pull back the jungle again.
她来自丛林
So she is from the jungle.
她的族人来自丛林
Her people are from the jungle.
他们坚称他们几乎回到过去了，不是吗？
So it's kind of they claimed it back
almost, haven't they?
谢谢
Gracias. Gracias.
有个群落，一个相当大的群落，在这儿
There is a community -
a proper community here.
所有的这些建筑现在给那些被迫来此
建造新城市的族人居住。
And all these buildings are now
used by the tribes that were forced
off the land to build the city,
他们还坚称，还是相当令人满意的。
so they've reclaimed it, which
is rather satisfying in a way...
不是对B总统满意，但是我发现
相当令人满意。
not for President Belaunde but I
find that really rather satisfying.
我认为这个旅程，这条路，我们正在
走着的，经历了诸多的变迁。
I think this journey - this road
we've been on - has taken so many
twists and turns in every sense.
我觉得意料之中的是，结局就像我们
沿途所遇见的那些事情一样新奇。
It actually doesn't surprise me
that the ending has been just as
strange as everything
we've found along the way.
本和修到达了他们路程的终点，
现在可以返乡了。
Ben and Hugh have
reached the end of their journey
and can now head for home.
过去的这8天里，他们横穿了秘鲁
Over the last eight days, they
have driven right across Peru,
在世界最危险的道路之一，
生还并讲述这个故事。
on one of the world's
most dangerous roads,
and survived to tell the tale.
我们得以穿越安第斯，深入雨林。
We were able to travel from
the Andes, deep into the rainforest.
我认为你不会在世界的任何地方找到
一条这么多变的道路
I don't think you'll find a road
with quite such variety
anywhere in the world.
这是个难以置信的惊心动魄之举
It's an incredibly
impressive enterprise, actually.
第一，他们在第一个地方发现的事实
简直就是个奇迹，我认为，
One, the fact they've got it
in the first place, which is
almost a miracle, I think.
第二，他们让事实不断浮现出来，
并让人们相信可以克服一切，
And, secondly, the fact they are
constantly clearing it and making
sure people can get through.
这是一次信任感的体验，开着车，
驾驭这么珍贵的一个宝物，真的。
It's a huge trust experience to
take the wheel and be in charge of
quite a precious cargo, really.
也有些奇怪的事情，比如
“左转，左转，否则你会杀了我们”
There was the odd kind of,
"Steer left, steer left,
or you're going to kill us!"
可是我觉得足够了
But I think that's fair enough.
我觉得所有的那些刺激的时刻，
开心的时刻，
I think all of those stressful
moments, happy moments...
正是这些构成了这次的旅行。不是吗？
that's what creates
the journey, isn't it? It's what
这些就是紧密连接我们的东西
bonds you together.
当我撞了挡板，佛格先生，
When I hit the dashboard, Mr
Fogle...
我想让你急刹车
I'd like you to
do an emergency stop.
你为什么开车？
Why are you driving?
你不觉得原本应该我来开吗？
我没撞过桥。
Don't you think I should be driving?
I didn't crash into a bridge.
我没撞过牛，不是吗？
I didn't hit a cow, did I?
你开的太颠簸了，
Yours is too bumpy, your driving.
你似乎不能搞定那些转弯
You don't seem able to cope
with bends.
你还陷泥巴里去过
You got stuck in the mud!
我们都陷泥巴里去过
We both got stuck in the mud.
(subtitle from http://shooter.cn by SPlayer™)
注意车辆，出租车！
Mind the motor, taxi!
(subtitle from http://shooter.cn by SPlayer™)